<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A caveat against flattery, and profanation of sacred things to secular ends upon sight of the order of the convention for the thanksgiving, and consideration of the misgovernment and misfortunes of the last race of kings of this nation.</title>
            <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61424</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5424</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R184625</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">20552741</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 20552741</idno>
            <idno type="VID">109453</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61424)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 109453)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 515:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A caveat against flattery, and profanation of sacred things to secular ends upon sight of the order of the convention for the thanksgiving, and consideration of the misgovernment and misfortunes of the last race of kings of this nation.</title>
                  <author>Stephens, Edward, d. 1706.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>36 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCLXXXIX [1689]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Edward Stephens (Socrates Christianus) by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  Church of England.</term>
               <term>Toadyism --  Religious aspects.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-09</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:109453:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:109453:1"/>
            <p>A CAVEAT AGAINST FLATTERY, AND PROFANATION OF <hi>Sacred</hi> things to <hi>Secular</hi> Ends: UPON <hi>Sight</hi> of the <hi>Order</hi> of the <hi>Convention</hi> for the <hi>Thanksgiving,</hi> AND <hi>Conſideration</hi> of the <hi>Miſgovernment</hi> and <hi>Misfortunes</hi> of the laſt Race of Kings of this Nation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:109453:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:109453:2"/>
            <head>A CAVEAT AGAINST FLATTERY, AND PROFANATION of <hi>Sacred</hi> things to <hi>Secular</hi> Ends.</head>
            <p>I Was not more pleaſed with the firſt <hi>News</hi> of the Order of the preſent Convention, for a <hi>Publick Thankſgiving</hi> to Almighty God, upon ſo juſt and admirable occaſion, than I was otherwiſe moved and diſturbed at the firſt <hi>Sight</hi> of their Order; to ſee all that lively ſenſe, which I expected, of ſuch an admirable Providence and Mercy of God to theſe Nations, in ſo ſeaſonable, ſo eaſie, and yet ſo great, and, if it be not our own fault, compleat Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, to dwindle (in my apprehenſion) into a kind of mean, ſervile, fawning Complement to the Prince, under a Formality of Religion. This hath filled me with variety of Thoughts, which I cannot forbear to communicate to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:109453:3"/>ſome of thoſe who are concern'd in it, I mean, the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Convention.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Prince</hi> I look upon as a perſon greatly to be eſteem'd, lov'd and honour'd, both for the Character generally gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of his Virtues, and more eſpecially, for that he ſeems to be choſen and deſign'd, by the Providence of God, for a ſpecial Inſtrument of great and deſirable matters in this Age; and hath been ſo already to this Nation. And therefore to aſſiſt him, and concur with him to thoſe ends, is in my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, an Act of Subſervience to the Divine Providence, which is <hi>a Glorious and Angelical Employment:</hi> but yet to expreſs our Reſpect to him, in ſuch a manner as this, whether through Flattery or Tranſport, I conceive is neither pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, decent, nor ſafe, either for him, or for the Nation.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Cauſe</hi> of this Publick Thankſgiving to Almighty God, is thus expreſſed: <hi>For having made His Highneſs, the Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>the Glorious Inſtrument of the Great Deliverance of this Kingdom, from Popery and Arbitrary Power.</hi> Whereas in truth the principal Cauſe of it is, not the <hi>Inſtrument,</hi> but the Great, and very great <hi>Deliverance;</hi> with many ſuch Circumſtances as are remarkable indicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ſpecial Providence, and over-ruling hand of God in it: And for this moſt ſolemn Thanks, ought to have been paid to Almighty God by this Nation, whoever had been the Inſtrument. And yet in this Order is there not one Word of this <hi>Great Deliverance,</hi> more than was neceſſary to expreſs what it was that the <hi>Prince of Orange</hi> was the Glorious Inſtrument of; as if his being the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was the Only, or the Principal thing, for which we were to give Thanks. I deny not but there was ſpecial reaſon to give Thanks for that alſo, as well as other Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, but then it ought to have been expreſs'd in its proper manner and order; the <hi>Deliverance</hi> firſt expreſly, with proper words of its due amplification, as the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal: and then by what <hi>Inſtrument,</hi> as is frequently added in the Scripture upon ſuch occaſions; <hi>by the hand of his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:109453:3"/>ſervant Moſes.</hi> And as our common form expreſſeth that which is above all, Gods <hi>ineſtimable Love in the Redemption of the World by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> It muſt therefore be confeſſed, that the principal matter of our Thankſgiving is in this Order either omitted, or mentioned only occaſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, ſo as to ſerve only to expreſs the other, at beſt in a prepoſterous manner. And this <hi>Inverſion of the proper and moſt natural and eaſie Order,</hi> is an Argument that it was ſo formed not by chance, but <hi>deſign,</hi> or to make the moſt charitable Conſtruction, through ſome <hi>inconſiderate Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port.</hi> And the ſame is obſervable in the <hi>Epithets</hi> given to each.</p>
            <p>I did never affect to contend about words, much leſs would I give occaſion of offence to ſuch an Aſſembly, of ſuch perſons, for a trifle; beſides, they that know me, know me to be a cordial friend, and well wiſher to this Convention, and who deſire to promote, not prejudice their Proceedings. But what I intend in this is no ſlight matter, nor will it ſo much prejudice, as be uſeful to them, and to others, if it be taken by the right handle, and as is intended. For from hence I obſerve <hi>two things, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve very ſerious conſideration and reflection upon them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The one a <hi>Defect</hi> of that due and profound Senſe of ſo great and undeſerved a Mercy, and of that anſwerable Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Gratitude to God, which our circumſtances and condition require. If we admit the form of the Order, to have proceeded only through <hi>Tranſport of Affection</hi> to the Prince, which is the moſt favourable conſtruction we can make of it, yet even that is an evidence of what I ſay, and that there was more reſpect to the Inſtrument, than to the Mercy it ſelf, or perhaps, to the Author of it, by ſome: for after the Author, the Mercy it ſelf is next to be conſider'd before the Inſtrument, as the principal Motive of our Gratitude; and the expreſſing it otherwiſe, is a kind or degree of neglect or ſlighting of the Mercy, and of diſreſpect to the Author: which a man may eaſily perceive,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:109453:4"/>if he do but conſider how ſuch an expreſſion of thanks, for ſome rare favour, would be reſented by a great Prince from ſome of his meaneſt Subjects. Would he not think him an Impertinent Fellow, and unworthy to be regarded, much more unworthy of ſuch a ſpecial favour? And if we admit that it paſſed the Houſes meerly through <hi>Inad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertence,</hi> which is alſo the moſt favourable Conſtruction we can make of that, this very Inadvertence is plainly an evidence of the ſame: for had we been affected as we ought, that would have made us more mindful and obſervant of ſuch a matter.</p>
            <p>But if it did proceed from <hi>Flattery,</hi> and deſign to Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement the Prince, and paſs, tho' obſerved, through <hi>Compliance,</hi> which might poſſibly be the caſe of ſome; that is not only unbecoming and below the Gravity of ſuch an Aſſembly, but a plain <hi>Profanation of Religion</hi> to baſe and unworthy ends, and greatly aggravates the former. And this is ſo plain of it ſelf, that I need not ſay more to prove or explain it. But whether either of theſe two, or both, was in the bottom, it is not a matter to be ſlighted, or lightly paſſed over. How great are the ſins of unſuitable Returns for extraordinary Mercies, and of Profanation of Religion to Secular ends, and the Judgments they uſually provoke, I leave to Divines to conſider more fully: But what are their Natural Effects and Conſequences, and what the Miſchiefs we have ſeen attending them, I think greatly neceſſary to be explained for our common Benefit, and neceſſary Caution for the future. We are juſt now entring upon a new Scene of Affairs, and if we well conſider the ſad Cataſtrophes of the two preceeding, and make juſt Enquiry into the cauſes thereof, we may meet with much matter of Admonition, Caution and Direction; and very pertinent to this purpoſe.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> I. his <hi>Mother</hi> and <hi>Grandfather</hi> having both born their own burdens, was, by the Providence of God, brought to the Throne of this Kingdom in Peace, even
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:109453:4"/>beyond the expectation of himſelf and many others. And though the reſtleſs and deſperate attempts of the Papiſts, were otherwiſe enough to terrifie a man of greater natural Courage than himſelf, yet he had for his Encouragement, an admirable experiment of the <hi>Special Providence of God,</hi> in the Preſervation of his next immediate Predeceſſor, Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> through a long Reign of forty four years, notwithſtanding all their Conſpiracies againſt her. And leſt that ſhould not ſufficiently affect him, he had moreover, in the very beginning of his Reign, a like expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riment thereof, in the Preſervation of himſelf, and his own Family from one of the moſt horrid, deſperate, and ſecret Conſpiracies, that the World hath ever heard of. And what did all this require of him? Could it be any thing leſs than the higheſt demonſtration of Gratitude to God, moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident Dependance upon him, and intire Fidelity to him? And what leſs from the Nation? But what was the <hi>Return?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was wiſely ſaid at his firſt coming in, by one of his <hi>Scotch</hi> Courtiers, to one of the <hi>Engliſh, We have brought you a good King, but you Court Flatterers will ſoon ſpoil him.</hi> And ſo it proved. It was indeed a great happineſs to have all Cauſes of Diſſention, not only in this Nation, but alſo between both Nations, ſo plainly and fully extinguiſh'd in his perſon. But ſuch was partly the <hi>Tranſport</hi> of all ſorts of people, and ſuch the groſs <hi>Flattery</hi> of many, that nothing was enough to magnify either his Wiſdom or his Power. This and the <hi>pompous Titles</hi> of Monarch, Abſolute, and Imperial Crown, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſoon raiſed his thoughts above the pitch of an <hi>Engliſh</hi> King. He thought himſelf as free to exceed the Laws of the Land, as God the Laws of Nature, when he ſaw occaſion for it; though he thought in Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſuch extraordinary Acts, like Miracles in Nature, were not ordinarily to be done. He thought the Rights and Liberties of the People, were but Indulgences wreſted from their Kings, his Predeceſſors, <hi>(cujus contrarium eſt ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum)</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:109453:5"/>and might thereupon infer, (and had wit enough to do it) that it was but reaſonable for him to regain by Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy, if he could, what they had loſt by Neceſſity or Conſtraint.</p>
            <p>Theſe fancies of his were continually fed and confirm'd by ſelf-ſeeking, flattering perſons; who, perceiving that to be the way to Preferment, ſtrained all their Wit and Parts to gratify his humour: and it was not long before he found occaſion to exerciſe that Freedom. The Diſcovery of that horrid Conſpiracy, which by his admirable Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance ſhould have confirmed his Dependance upon the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Providence for the future, having a contrary effect upon him, he caſt about to ſecure his Safety and Quiet by his own <hi>Craft and Policy.</hi> And the only way for that he conceived was by making not only Amity and Leagues, but the neareſt Alliance that could be, with ſome Potent Prince of the Popiſh Religion. And by all means he muſt have a match for his Son either from <hi>France</hi> or <hi>Spain:</hi> for the Accompliſhment whereof the Pope, whom he had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore aſſerted to be Anti-chriſt, muſt be complemented with no meaner Title than <hi>Sanctiſſime Pater;</hi> Indulgence to Papiſts, contrary to the Laws, muſt be agreed, and the effectual Execution of the Laws againſt them actually ſtopp'd by ſecret Orders; for a publick Declaration for that purpoſe, would not then paſs for a Legal Act of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſing Power. And becauſe they, who were moſt Zea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous in Religion, were like to be moſt averſe from compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in theſe things, <hi>the very Power of Religion</hi> muſt be <hi>diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>countenanced under the Notion of Puritaniſm;</hi> and Indifference and <hi>Formality incouraged under the Notion of Loyalty, Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Conformity.</hi> And to this end was the <hi>Book of Sports</hi> injoyned to be read in Churches, and many Pious and able Divines put out of their Employments, if not Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holds too, for refuſing to read it. Nor did he want incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement in all theſe things from Flatterers of all ſorts, who eaſily prevailed againſt the ſounder and ſafer Counſels
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:109453:5"/>of others. And though ſome of them, who had publiſhed their falſe and flattering Argument in Print, were queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in Parliament for it, both in King <hi>James,</hi> and in King <hi>Charles</hi> I time; yet even for ſome of them did the King intercede in Parliament; as King <hi>James,</hi> 7. <hi>Jac.</hi> for Dr. <hi>Cowel;</hi> and others were preferr'd or favoured afterward, as Dr. <hi>Mainwaring</hi> by King <hi>Charles</hi> I. as others ſince have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten what they wrote for, and have been well rewarded for their pains. Of the former ſort ſee <hi>Ruſhworth,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Petyts Miſcellanea Parlementaria;</hi> of theſe latter, 'tis like the Parliament in due time will take notice.</p>
            <p>This unhappy Policy, as it was not unlike in its Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to that of <hi>Jeroboam,</hi> which <hi>became a ſin to his Houſe, even to cut it off, and deſtroy it from off the face of the earth,</hi> ſo it proved alſo in its conſequence. His eldeſt and hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Son Prince <hi>Henry,</hi> was in the beginning of theſe cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, and ſoon after the firſt propoſal of ſuch a match, taken away by an immature death; and <hi>himſelf</hi> perſiſting therein, by a death queſtioned then, and in the dark to this day, whether not untimely. His next Son and Succeſſor King <hi>Charles</hi> I. whom he had involved in theſe ſnares, but never lived to ſee his Marriage accompliſhed, proceeding in the like courſes, giving incouragement to Flatterers, and through their falſe and deceitful Counſels, in many things tranſgreſſing the Laws, indulging to Papiſts, and diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raging and oppreſſing many of the moſt Religious and Conſcientious of the Proteſtants, as Puritans and Factious, and renewing with more ſeverity, that unhappy Policy of the <hi>Book of Sports;</hi> at laſt concluded this Scene with that unhappy Cataſtrophe, which is well known to the World.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Charles</hi> I. having alſo born his burden, to his Son, <hi>King Charles the Second,</hi> after he had been tutor'd in a Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſs of twelve years Exile, was Almighty God pleaſed to open the Gates of his Mercy; and when all hopes ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from Foreign Aſſiſtance, or Domeſtick Conſpiracies ſailed, then by a favourable and manifeſt Providence to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:109453:6"/>or rather conduct him to his Fathers Throne in Peace, to the great Joy of himſelf and the whole Nation, putting into his hand, upon terms of his Behaviour, the prize of a fair opportunity, to have made himſelf, and theſe Nations happy, had he had a heart to it, and they been diſpoſed for it. But ſuch was the <hi>Tranſport</hi> they were all under at that time, that they ſoon forgot themſelves, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got God, and, like Pigs to the Trough, ran greedily to a brutiſh enjoyment of their unexpected Happineſs; and through their Ingratitude to God, inſtead of Bleſſings, which they might have been, proved mutual Temptations, and occaſions of Corruption and Debauchery each to other; the new King by a moſt pernicious evil Example, and thoſe about him by ſelf-ſeeking Flattery, Compliance, and Imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation: whereby they both encouraged and hardened him in thoſe evil Courſes, and propagated the Imitation of it to all ranks of people.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Parliament</hi> it ſelf, that is, the Majority, unadvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedly and contrary to the true Conſtitution of this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>declared him</hi> to be, by the Fundamental Laws of this Kingdom, <hi>in effect above all Law,</hi> and his very <hi>Officers irreſiſtible;</hi> and required of all Officers of Corporations, Officers and Souldiers in the Militia, and of the Clergy and Univerſities, a Declaration to the ſame effect; ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected the <hi>Dwelling-houſes of the People</hi> to be ſearched at the pleaſure of his Officers; formed a new <hi>Militia,</hi> and put it wholly into his Hands; and profuſely gave him <hi>vaſt ſumms of Money,</hi> out of the Eſtates of the people, beyond all need, reaſon and juſtice. The Commiſſioners and Convocations of <hi>the Clergy,</hi> in their new Additions to the Common Prayer, without any regard to what he or his Succeſſors might prove in time, or to the inconvenience they might thereby bring upon themſelves, needleſsly gave him the Title of <hi>moſt Religious and Gracious,</hi> in publick forms of moſt ſolemn addreſs to Almighty God; and the <hi>Kings Arms</hi> were in divers Churches in the City, ſet above the Commandments
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:109453:6"/>of God in the place of moſt ſolemn Worſhip; whereas at <hi>Oxford,</hi> as I have heard, the Founders Arms in the Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, being placed above the Kings, were ordered to be taken down for the Indecency. Agreeable hereunto was <hi>Loyalty</hi> (as they call'd Compliance with the Will and Pleaſure of the King, whether legal or not) cry'd up as the only Honeſty, and <hi>Non-Reſiſtauce</hi> and <hi>Paſſive-Obedience,</hi> as if they were the greateſt and moſt neceſſary Doctrines of Religion, by all who ſought the Favour of the Times, in their ordinary Diſcourſe and Converſation, and publickly ſo aſſerted in Speeches, in Sermons from the Pulpit, and in Printed Books, by ſuch as expected any ſpecial Favour or Preferment.</p>
            <p>Nor ſtay'd it here, for <hi>the King</hi> now aſſured by ſuch De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrations of the Obedience and Compliance of his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and thereby encouraged to take the Liberty to grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his Luſt more openly than otherwiſe perhaps he would have done; and being a Perſon of a pleaſant Wit, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting in Repertees, Jeſts and ſuch like Diverſions from ſerious thoughts, the ſtream of <hi>the Courtiers, Gallants,</hi> and all who affected to be reputed ſuch, preſently ran with a full torrent into the ſame Chanel, and ſoon overſpread a great part of the Nation. And vain aiery <hi>Lightneſs,</hi> fro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and <hi>Obſcene Diſcourſe,</hi> profane and horrid <hi>Swearing,</hi> and more then brutiſh ſatisfaction <hi>of Luſt,</hi> and <hi>Contempt of all Religion,</hi> were not only indulged, but affected too as generous qualities of a Gentleman, and certain Notes and Evidences of Loyalty and Fidelity to the King, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſormity to his own heart and mind. And thoſe, who made any ſcruple of Conſcience to run to the ſame Exceſs of Riot, were looked upon and deſpiſed as diſaffected, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyal, mean ſpirited fools, and Fanaticks; but thoſe who did dare to oppoſe either the Debaucheries of theſe Loya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, or the illegal actions of the King, as Imprudent, Raſh, and Madmen. And ſo great a <hi>Baſeneſs and Degeneracy</hi> thereupon preſently ſeiſed and tainted many, that, not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:109453:7"/>conſidering the ſevere Denunciations of our Saviour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch, they were even out-faced and aſhamed of their Religion, and became <hi>Hypocrites in Debauchery;</hi> and, to avoid the Imputation and Reproach of being religious and ſneaking, did actually ſneak to ſuch degenerate and deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable Wretches, while by baſe compliance in obſcene Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and familiar Swearing, they gloried in their ſhame, and would ſeem companions with them in ſuch things, as yet they never acted indeed. And in ſo degenerate a ſtate what can be ſo abſurd and inconſiſtant that Men will not do? What wonder is it then to ſee Men at the ſame time in Words applaud the Non-Obedience of the Biſhops, and yet in their acts comply with the Diſpenſing Power? To ſee thoſe, who by their High Profeſſions of Loyalty and Non-Reſiſtance, had invited and encouraged the King to uſe his liberty to inſlave them, when they found that he, preſuming too much upon their High Profeſſion, was like indeed to involve them in the ſame Slavery and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefs with the reſt, chooſe rather to enter with others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſecret Conſpiracies for the Common Safety, than in time (to prevent that) with a true and generous Loyalty and Fidelity openly oppoſe his Illegal Proceedings; Theſe things, with ſome few others made the Government of King <hi>Charles</hi> II. uneaſy, and brought King <hi>James</hi> II. to his <hi>Exit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are now entring, as I ſaid, into <hi>a New Scene of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs:</hi> And that this may proceed more happily, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be of great uſe to reflect upon and conſider well <hi>the Errors, Miſcarriages, and true Cauſes of the unhappineſs and ſad Cataſtrophes of the two former.</hi> I have already brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touched ſome of the more immediate and viſible Cauſes, Hiſtorically as to the matter of <hi>Fact:</hi> But to make a right uſe of them, it may be neceſſary to enquire a little more deeply and Philoſophically into them. Theſe <hi>Cauſes</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, to go to the bottom, are <hi>two-fold,</hi> Natural, and Divine, which doth ſecretly but effectually diſpoſe and order the Natural. The <hi>Divine</hi> is by way of <hi>Judgment,</hi> which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:109453:7"/>juſt, and for ſome <hi>Sin,</hi> and doth frequently proceed to Exciſion, cutting off, and Extirpation of whole Families, when the ſin is perſiſted in; though for the moſt part, unleſs in caſe of ſome heinous crime, gradually giving fair warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings and opportunities to one after another, to prevent by Reformation the final and utter Extirpation of all. And though many times the Root of Bitterneſs lye deep, and be hard by others to be detected, yet it is not ſeldom that the <hi>Sin</hi> is legible and apparent in the <hi>Puniſhment;</hi> and cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly if we well conſider what a Sin it is <hi>to reſiſt, oppoſe, and oppreſs the Truth</hi> when offered, eſpecially in matters of great conſequence, and preſented by ſome ſpecial Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence of God, all who believe <hi>Popery</hi> to be an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Abuſe and Corruption of the genuine Chriſtianity, tending to the defacing, enervating, and ſubverſion of it, and that the <hi>Reformation</hi> deſired is nothing but the Reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of it to its priſtine and genuine Luſtre and Power, muſt of neceſſity believe that the <hi>Cheriſhing of Popery</hi> and <hi>Oppoſing</hi> of ſuch a <hi>Reformation,</hi> may be ſuch a Sin as, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſiſted in, may provoke as great Judgments as this. And then if we reflect back as far as the <hi>Grand-father</hi> of our <hi>King</hi> James <hi>the Firſt,</hi> and thence obſerve how Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence and Favour to Popery, from this firſt Oppoſing of the Reformation in <hi>Scotland,</hi> has been continued and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually attended with deſtructive ſignal Judgments in his Poſterity ever ſince, beginning with one very Prodigious, a horrid Dream, of the loſs of both his Arms, and the ſudden Death of both his Sons, all at diſtant places in one Night, as may be ſeen in <hi>Spotſwood;</hi> it will not be hard to trace and detect the True Root which hath born all this bitter Fruit in that Family. And they who cannot diſcern this in that Family alone, may for their confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion take alſo into conſideration the <hi>Occurrences</hi> of a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporary Family</hi> in our Neighbour County, <hi>France,</hi> that of <hi>Valois</hi> from <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. to its Extirpation; and compare with theſe two the long and happy <hi>Reign of Q</hi> Elizabeth,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:109453:8"/>againſt which the Gates of Hell could not prevail. And if with all theſe we conſider alſo <hi>the Actions and Cataſtro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phe of</hi> Hen. 4. <hi>of</hi> France, and the monſtrous Wickedneſs and Barbarous Cruelties of the preſent King, it will not be hard to make a <hi>Moral Prediction</hi> of the like fate attending this <hi>Family of</hi> Bourbon alſo. This, it is very probable, if we conſider the Original and Progreſs <hi>pari paſſu</hi> all along of both Sin and Puniſhment, was <hi>the Provoking Sin and Root of Bitterneſs,</hi> which by Divine Judgment hath expoſed them to the <hi>ſtrong Deluſions,</hi> which have been the more immediate and apparent Cauſes of all their Miſcarriages and Unhappineſs. And though it may be hoped Men are now near as well cured of Popery, as the Jews of Idolatry, yet may this Obſervation afford us a very <hi>neceſſary Admonition</hi> at this time, if we be not like the Horſe and Mule: For certainly that Soul which in theſe occurrances of this Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al Family within the Period before mentioned, cannot diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern a continued courſe of Providence powerfully operate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing therein, is deeply immerſed in Senſuality, and very Brutiſh. It is therefore very <hi>reaſonable that at this time we do ſeriouſly conſider</hi> the Courſe of Gods Providence and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon that Family; that it was not any Favour to Popery, otherwiſe than as that is an Abuſe and Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the true Religion, that was <hi>the Sin of that Family;</hi> nor was it that alone, but that and other Abuſes by Prophanation and Connivance; That the <hi>Prince</hi> is <hi>deſcended</hi> from that Family, from which he may derive a load of Guilt upon himſelf, by participation in any of thoſe ſins, by forgetfulneſs of God, and by neglect of thoſe Duties, which this late extraordinary Providence calls him unto: That <hi>the preſent State of the Nation</hi> is a moſt vitious and degenerate State; and that ſo extraordinary Deliverance, when greater Judgments might reaſonably have been expected, obligeth to great Seriouſneſs, affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Senſe of the ſpecial Providence of God in it, and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual Reformation: for great and undeſerved Mercies do
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:109453:8"/>not leſs oblige (either in force or extent) than the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere Judgments: And to conſider that <hi>the ſame Providence of God,</hi> which effected all this, <hi>can</hi> eaſily, and certainly will, <hi>turn all again</hi> into Confuſion and a greater Judgment, if we do not wiſely indeavour to concur with it, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer his ends. He can take away the Prince, and incline the Princeſs to recall the King; he can by impeding or croſſing our Preparations for <hi>Ireland,</hi> or an unexpected defeat of part of them, diſcourage the reſt, and incourage the <hi>Iriſh;</hi> he can raiſe up a deſperate Party at home, and from a cloud of an hand breadth make them cover the Land; he can ſend a Spirit of Diviſion amongſt us and Confound our Counſels; of Infatuation, as he did amongſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> to reſolve, with great imaginary Wiſdom, and Subtilty, upon the direct and moſt effectual means of our Ruine and Deſtruction. And by theſe, and many other unconceiveable ways and means, can he eaſily and quickly turn all our Tranſport into Mourning and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion.</p>
            <p>This, I ſay, <hi>he can</hi> do, and <hi>we may</hi> provoke him to do it, in part or in whole, if we, like Dogs, greedily catch up the Bone, and regard not the Maſters hand that threw it, but continue in that brutiſh Stupidity, which hath ſo much prevailed in this Nation. And it may be conſidered, <hi>whether we have not already provoked</hi> him to let us ſtruggle with ſome <hi>Difficulties,</hi> which might eaſily have been pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented: The ſo eaſie Compliance, or Inadvertence, in paſſing <hi>the Order</hi> in the Form aforeſaid, was plainly a Fault, and ſuch as I cannot think it conſiſtent with true Piety, and due ſence of the Majeſty and Honour of God, for any Mortal to offer to excuſe it; and certainly nothing could be a more proper Correction of ſuch an <hi>Eaſineſs</hi> or Inadver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, than to permit the ſame perſons, in their Debates, to run themſelves into ſuch Difficulties, with loſs of time, as might as eaſily have been avoided, as the Order have been amended. We have been ſo long impoſed upon with
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:109453:9"/>Words, that like Children, we are eaſily allured and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried with ſome, and frighted with others, without any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. This being perceived, an Expedient was ſought, but ſuch an one choſen as made all the Queſtion; whereas I doubt not that the matter might have been propoſed at firſt in ſuch commodious terms and expreſſions, and ſo enforced with Reaſons and Demonſtrations, as that it would have paſſed as eaſily as another Vote did at that time, and with no inconſiderable advantage. And if this be ſo, why might there not be ſome ſecret energy of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, or Subtraction of a more favourable Direction in it? This may be too nice a Speculation for this Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration: But this I know, that the very thoughts of men are not ſo much in their own power as they imagine, but are ſubject to the Power, not only of God, but of much inferiour Spirits by his permiſſion; and he is no great Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſopher, who doth not perceive it, nor very knowing Chriſtian, who doth not believe it. And were it under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood how intimately and effectually his Providence doth interpoſe in all things, perhaps there would not be much doubt of what I ſay: But they that underſtand theſe things may make their uſe of them.</p>
            <p>Of the other <hi>more immediate and more apparent Cauſes,</hi> there is one that is <hi>Prophanation of Religion,</hi> which hath a <hi>double Efficacy,</hi> Moral and Natural: <hi>Moral, as a ſin</hi> provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Gods Diſpleaſure and Judgments, and ſo is compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in what I have ſaid before. <hi>Natural</hi> in reſpect of its <hi>Contagious and Spreading Nature,</hi> and of the miſchievous Effects and Conſequences of it. All <hi>evil Examples,</hi> eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of perſons of great Place, and among people diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to receive Impreſſions from them, are very Infectious; but none more than Irreligion and Prophaneneſs, partly thro' the <hi>Senſuality</hi> of men in the Corrupt State of Nature, which is eaſily affected with Objects of Sence, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore apt for them to neglect and contemn things of a more refined and Spiritual Nature, and partly through the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:109453:9"/>and Efficacy of the envious Apoſtate Spirits, who, of all things, are moſt gratified with it, and moſt active to promote it; and for this cauſe there is the more reaſon to check and ſuppreſs the very firſt and leaſt appearances of it; for a little Leven leveneth the whole Lump; but yet more if we conſider alſo the pernicious <hi>Effects and Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences</hi> of it, even <hi>of a natural growth</hi> and production: For it is plainly a direct Introduction to Irreligion, and thereby an Inlet to all manner of Diſorder, in Perſons, Families, and States, as may plainly be perceived by this Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>True Religion</hi> in man is a Coeleſtial Influence and Divine Power, received and embraced by a Soul rightly prepared and diſpoſed by true Information and good Inſtruction, whereby that Soul is ennobled and exalted to a degree of Excellence above the Humane Nature, according to the Degree of that reception. This illuminates his mind, and makes him ſenſible that he is a Dependant Being, hath his Dependance upon a Being moſt Excellent, and ſo affects him that he reſteth on it, and directeth all his motions to it, as his proper and only Centre: Hence proceed theſe happy Effects, he moves orderly, his Soul being fix'd upon its proper and ſatisfactory Object, runs not aſtray, nor affects any other with any diſorderly Motion; ſo that he keeps his rank and place in the Univerſe, without diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance to himſelf or others: and this produceth a free and generous Magnanimity, he admires not the Grandeur of the World, fears no Man, flatters no Man, but deals plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſincerely with all; pitties their Weakneſs, even in injuries and affronts to himſelf, as of People of diſtempered mind, is Communicative, and ready and induſtrious to do good to all.</p>
            <p>On the contrary <hi>Irreligion</hi> indiſpoſeth the Soul for that Divine Principle, whence it becomes dry and narrow, like a withered Branch, and unhingeth it from its proper Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre, whence proceedeth all manner of Diſorder: Firſt, it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:109453:10"/>directs all its motions to it ſelf, as its Centre, as if it were independent. But not being really ſo, it cannot reſt there; but runs out after ſomething elſe; and miſſing its proper Object, falls upon ſome falſe Appearance, and proſecutes it, as its proper Object with a motion ſuitable to that, and ſo exorbitant and irregular. And hence proceeds all that Degeneracy of Mind, that Admiration and Inſatiable proſecution of the Pleaſures of the Fleſh, and Grandeur of the World, and all that Baſeneſs, Falſeneſs, Flattery, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidiouſneſs and Treachery which hath ſo infected and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted this Nation.</p>
            <p>The Religion before deſeribed is that which is proper to uncorrupted Nature: <hi>The Chriſtian Religion</hi> comprehends all that and more. It not only acquaints us with the <hi>Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal of all the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nhappineſs of Mankind,</hi> which the ſacred An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquities of the Jews did in ſome ſort before; but it plainly reveals unto us <hi>the proper and only Remedy,</hi> which the Jews Religion did but obſcurely ſignifie by Types and Figures: That man is ſo inconſiderable a being in himſelf, and ſo corrupted and polluted by Sin, that he cannot poſſibly have any acceſs to the Great, and Glorious, and Holy God, without which he muſt be eternally miſerable, but by a <hi>Holy Mediator:</hi> That the Great, and Glorious, and Holy God notwithſtanding out of meer compaſſion to his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpicable Creature, hath provided ſuch a Mediator for us, in whom he hath united the Divine and Humane Nature in one perſon: That this Mediator having upon the Theatre of this Earth performed a moſt exact obedience to the Will of God, even to death, did thereby offer up the Humane Nature a Sacrifice, and conſecrate it to God: That thereby he obtained favour with God for all Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and a Right of Dominion over them; and is aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cended into Heaven as the Captain of our Salvaton, where he interceeds for, and thence diſperſes his Divine Gifts to all that receive him, and by Purity, Holineſs, and Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, in Obedience to his Holy Law, and Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:109453:10"/>to his moſt Holy Motions, firmly adhere to him; and in due time will Judge and Condemn all his Enemies, and all thoſe ungrateful and perfideous Wretches, inveag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by them to deſert his Service.</p>
            <p>Concerning this Religion, it is a moſt true and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Obſervation and Concluſion of that profound Search<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er into Nature, Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> (7. <hi>de Augm. Sci.</hi> c. 1.) that in almoſt all Creatures, but eſpecially in Man, if he be not degenerate, there is an appetite to a two-fold good, one of the Community, the other of the indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual, of which the former is the moſt prevalent, <hi>[as we may obſerve in Animals, which will readily expoſe themſelves to ſuch danger for the preſervation of their young, from which they would otherwiſe moſt timorouſly have fled for the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of themſelves,]</hi> and that of all Religions there is none, which doth ſo much tend to the Promotion of the Publick Good before the Private, as the Holy Chriſtian Religion. <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nde liquido pateat,</hi> &amp;c. From whence, ſaith he, it doth plainly appear, that it was one and the ſame God, who gave to all his Creatures thoſe Laws of Nature, and to Men the Laws of Chriſt,</p>
            <p>Upon theſe Conſiderations, which contain great truths, though but briefly and plainly expreſſed, it is very evident That the true Chriſtian Religion, even by a natural way of cauſation, is a moſt excellent Means even for the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Weal and Happineſs of Perſons, Families, and States, both Governors and Governed: That it ought even upon that account by all wiſe Governors, to be promoted as a matter of great concern, with all care and reſolution: and that Irreligion and Prophaneneſs are even by way of natural cauſation the Inlets of all manner of Evil and Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief both to Perſons, Families, and States; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſtrictly and ſeverely to be ſuppreſſed in the very firſt eruption, as a dangerous and contagious Plague.</p>
            <p>Hence alſo it is evident, that the natural Effects of the <hi>Debaucheries of Covetouſneſs and Ambition,</hi> are as perniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:109453:11"/>to all Societies as thoſe of Whoreing and Drinking, and produce as great Diſorders: For when the Soul is once unhinged from its proper Centre, it proſecutes the miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken Object, it next fixeth upon, be it what it will, with the ſame diſorderly motions, becauſe it proſecuteth it inſtead of its proper Object, and under the notion of that: and that therefore theſe are by all wiſe Governors to be taken care of, that they be reſtrained and all incentives and occaſions of them removed and avoided.</p>
            <p>And here it may be fit to take notice of <hi>two great Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of this kind of Debauchery amongſt us,</hi> which were <hi>great Errors in Government in King</hi> James 1. and his Poſterity; the conferring of Titles of Honour, and the conferring of Places and Preferments in Church and State upon improper and unworthy Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Titles of Honour</hi> they are properly Enſigns of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue and Merit, and ought to be Rewards only of that, and Encouragements to it; but when they are conferred upon perſons for Money, by way of Sale, or upon Men for their Eſtates without any proſpect of their Vertue or Merit, by this means theſe Rewards and Encouragements, due only to Vertue and Merit, are withdrawn from it, and given to Avarice and Ambition, and thereby made Incentives to them. And, to note it by the by, the promiſcuous confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of Titles of Honour unduly makes them inſignificant, and is very injurious to all, who have juſtly obtained them.</p>
            <p>And for <hi>Places and Preferments</hi> the granting of them for Money, or upon any other conſideration than the proper Qualifications of the perſons for diſcharge of the Duty, or even to covetous or ambitious perſons, in many caſes, though otherwiſe well qualified, beſides that it is a great Errour in Government in other reſpects, as to this preſent purpoſe, it gives great incouragement to ſuch to ſeek to get them by indirect means; and the evil <hi>Example</hi> of Men, in ſeeking after Preferments, and in their behaviour in them, tends very much to the corrupting of the reſt of the people, and infecting them with theſe Vices.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:109453:11"/>
            <p>But no Examples of this kind are ſo pernicious as thoſe <hi>of the Clergy.</hi> It is a great truth that when Vertue fails in them, Faith will fail in the people. If they who in their Baptiſmal Vows have renounced the World, the Pomps and Vanities, and Superfluities of the World, and are moreover conſecrated to the ſpecial Service of God, and obliged by their Profeſſion to teach, as well by Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, as by Doctrine, Heavenly-mindedneſs and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the World, ſhall ſo forſake that, and follow this World, as to turn that Sacred Profeſſion into a Trade as a means to get Riches and Honours, and live plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifully; and even outdo the men of the World in unſatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble proſecution of theſe things; what a Temptation muſt this be to all others to do the like in their way! Nothing can be more abſurd and inconſiſtent than Coveteouſneſs, Ambition, Pride, and Indulgence to the Enjoyments of the World, with the Profeſſion of a Miniſter of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel of Chriſt. Even Riches and Wealth in a Clergyman, unleſs he be as rich in Good Works, is, in my apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a Scandalous and Nauſcious thing. And ſuch uſually prove miſchievous Inſtruments both in Church and State, if favoured, or ſuffered to grow too great in either.</p>
            <p>King <hi>Charles</hi> II. by his Prodigality (which was increaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Prodigality of his Parliament) and by ſuffering himſelf to be cheated and abuſed, being often in want of money, for ſupply of that was forced after ſome time to corrupt, by <hi>Penſions and Perferments,</hi> the members of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament to betray their truſt and feed his Prodigality with the Peoples Money. Theſe Examples of thoſe who no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toriouſly cheated him, and of himſelf in corrupting thoſe Publick Truſtees, and other ſuch abuſes, were no leſs effectual to the <hi>Corrupting the Manners of the Nation in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of Juſtice and Honeſty,</hi> than were his other Debauche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries in reſpect of Temperance and Sobriety. And yet it may be a queſtion, Whether the greedy <hi>Purſuite of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments</hi> by our Clergy-men, and their ill and irregular
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:109453:12"/>Uſe of them, either hourding up Riches, or miſemploying them in a ſecular, or luxurious way of living, have not been as miſchievous Examples to infect peoples minds with Over-valuation of the World, and the Pomps and Vanities thereof, as any of thoſe other with other Vices? This is more notorious than that I need either to ſcruple the men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or uſe many words to convince others of the truth of it; and doth much incline me to think it very neceſſary that ſome effectual courſe be taken, to reduce our Clergy to a more Philoſophical way of living, or that none but who are ſo diſpoſed may be admitted to any great Preferments.</p>
            <p>This may poſſibly offend ſome, but no good Chriſtian, I am confident: and therefore to ſtop the Mouths of all ſuch, I will give one inſtance of ſo notorious a defect of good Employment of the large Revenues of our Church, as ſhall make the beſt and greateſt of our Clergymen lay their hands upon their Mouths. It is now one hundred and forty years ſince the Reformed Religion, which had received ſome interruption by Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> was reſtored and eſtabliſhed by Queen <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> about the beginning of that Age, Almighty God by his Special Providence had produced two things of great Conſequence in the World, the Reſtauration of Learning, facilitated by a new and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Invention of Printing, and a Diſcovery of a new World, of Barbarous Ignorant People, by the help of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther late Invention and Improvement of Navigation. We have had as great advantages of acceſs thither, and to all parts of the World as any People; but what uſe have we made of this, and of all our great Learning, and large Revenues? What ſenſe have we expreſſed of the wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Goodneſs of God to Mankind, of the Labours of our Saviour and his Apoſtles, of the Zeal of the primitive Chriſtians, and of the Obligation of all theſe Examples? What Devotion to God; What charity to the Souls of Men? So far have we been from that, that the very Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rizaical Zeal of the Jeſuites and other Romiſh Emiſſaries
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:109453:12"/>could not move us to the leaſt degred of Emulation, which hath not been wanting upon other occaſions. But what wonder is all this when our Devotion and Zeal for the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God and good of Souls hath ſcarce extended ſo ſar as <hi>Ireland?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The truth is, it is no wonder if ſuch Abundance of <hi>the World</hi> choak and ſtifle all Motions and Activity of this kind. Our very Liturgy doth reproach us with <hi>Lazineſs and Coldneſs,</hi> and is a publick Monument to condemn us. The very <hi>Defects</hi> in our Reformation, which could not be remedied at the firſt compoſure of that Book, but are there noted that it might be done in due time, remain un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reformed as they were to this very time, notwithſtanding the various conditions we have ſince been in, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other Alterations we could eaſily make.</p>
            <p>We have not reſtored any thing of the true Chriſtian and <hi>Ancient Diſcipline</hi> of the Church, but oppoſed and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed thoſe who have deſired it, and inſtead thereof re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained only a Popiſh Relict and Abuſe of it; have by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Laws forced ſuch into the Church, as according to the true Chriſtian Diſcipline ought to have been caſt out; and inſtead of preſerving the Honour of Chriſtianity, help<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Serpent to caſt out a Flood of Scandals to eclipſe it. We have not reſtored <hi>the peculiar Solemnity of the Chriſtian Worſhip,</hi> without which our Service, in the judgment of Biſhop <hi>Andrews,</hi> is imperfect and defective, to its proper and frequent uſe; but inſtead thereof ſet up ſuch a kind of Form, to be read with great formality at the Altar, as was heretofore introduced, and preſently, after exploded in <hi>France,</hi> as a dry and barren Novelty.</p>
            <p>And for our <hi>Preaching</hi> in which we glory, how much hath it been abuſed to pleaſe Princes, and to pleaſe and maintain Parties; to perſwade people out of their natural rights under pretence of Loyalty, and into Slavery under the notion of Paſſive Obedience, that thereby they might preach themſelves into Preferments! And for thoſe <hi>great
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:109453:13"/>Chriſtian Virtues</hi> of Humility, contempt of the World, Heavenly-mindedneſs, Frequent and Earneſt Prayers and Faſting, and Zeal and Induſtry for the Service of God and Salvation of Souls, ſo much recommended in the Goſpel, not only by Word, but by the Example alſo of our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our, his Apoſtles, and the primitive Chriſtians, and which are noted by a Heathen Hiſtorian, to have made the Country Clergy in his time venerable in the ſight of God and Man, how little thereof is there now to be met with among our Clergy? So little that I doubt not but we are now as much over ſpread with Phariſniſm, (except the beſt part of it) as were the Jews in our Saviours time. And what may be <hi>the Cauſe</hi> into which all this may be truly reſolved? Certainly nothing but after an ill and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſiderate <hi>Education,</hi> the falſe Appearances of the World, and the great <hi>Preferments</hi> which are attainable by compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with the pleaſure of thoſe who have the diſpoſing of them. This is it which hath betrayed both King and Country, as I ſhall preſently ſhew more particularly.</p>
            <p>I do not impute it to the Greatneſs of the Preferments, which are Talents, whereof a good Man may make a good uſe, though few have been made better men by them, ſo much as to want of good Education, and the <hi>unhappy courſe</hi> which was <hi>taken in the diſpoſal of many of them. Great Preferments</hi> are Temptations and Allurements to Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous and Ambitious Men to uſe any means to obtain them. Theſe being all at the Diſpoſal of the King, and King <hi>James</hi> I. dividing the Common Intereſt, by ſetting up pretended Prorogative againſt the Laws, made uſe of this Power to encreaſe and ſtrengthen his party. And though this courſe proved very unſucceſsful to Him and his Son; yet King <hi>Charles</hi> II. fell likewiſe into the ſame Error, forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his Solemn Promiſes from <hi>Bredah,</hi> he induſtriouſly, as ſome ſay, fomented differences between the two parties of the Clergy; however he too eaſily conſented to that <hi>miſchievious Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> which made an actual Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:109453:13"/>and was therefore, as it is believed, ſecretly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted by the Papiſts. By this means were many good and uſeful men excluded from all Preferments and Employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Church. And though of thoſe who con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed there were many too eminent for their Worth to be paſſed by, yet generally Prerogative Men were the Men who were preferred. And this was it which filled the Church with Covetous, Proud, Ambitious, Worldly Men, and Court Flatterers.</p>
            <p>And to note it by the way that curſed <hi>Dividing of the Church</hi> and Nation, by that miſchievous Act of Uniform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, no leſs contrary to Chriſtian Prudence then Chriſtian Charity, proved another great Error in Policy and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, no leſs inconſiſtent with civil, than Chriſtian Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, and made his Government uneaſie, which might otherwiſe by performance of his Word have been made moſt eaſie through a general Unanimity, and mutual E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulations for his Service and the Common Good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Flattery,</hi> the other immediate and apparent cauſe of the Evils aforeſaid, is the natural product and off-ſpring of thoſe Debaucheries of Covetouſneſs and Ambition, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I have been ſpeaking: For the Gratification of theſe is the only or moſt common <hi>End</hi> it aims at. And its natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Effects are that it ſubtilly, dangerouſly, and pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly abuſeth, deceives and betrays, under the ſpecious pretence of great Affection, Reſpect and Service; and ſo much the more dangerouſly and perniciouſly, by how much the more ſubtilly: and therefore is in men of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt parts (Clergy men eſpecially) if once found Unſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, Covetous or Ambitious, with ſo much the greater Caution to be ſuſpected and avoided, even by the wiſeſt of Men, who otherwiſe may be ſubject to its inſinuations, and impoſed on by it.</p>
            <p>King <hi>James</hi> the Firſt was certainly a Man of no mean or ordinary Wit, and parts in other reſpects, but his Affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of an uncontrolable Abſoluteneſs, and his Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſneſs,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:109453:14"/>expoſed him to the crafts of evil Men. He knew well enough that he was bound and obliged by Laws: that was too plain to be denied, and therefore he made no ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple to profeſs as much in general in Parliament. But under the umbrage of that Profeſſion, took liberty to tranſgreſs his bounds in many Particulars, upon pretence of Law and Prorogative. To make this paſs the more clearly, it was neceſſary he ſhould incline two ſorts of Men, the Biſhops and the Judges, as much as might be to his Service, which could not better and more craftily be effected, than by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up the Authority of both as high as might be: For this carried an appearance of Favour to them, and moreover made them the more ſerviceable to him, he having the choice of the perſons. Upon this the Judges were apt to ſtrain the Law to comply with his deſires; but the Biſhops and their dependants, the Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellors, and Civilians, and the Epiſcopal Clergy, were ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally for magnifying the Prorogative without conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of, or regard to the bounds preſcribed by the Laws and Conſtitution of the Government, partly as the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Intereſt of their party, but more eſpecially as the direct way to gain the Kings Favour and Preferments. This produced Flatterers in abundance, who ſtrained their Wits by plauſible Arguments grounded upon ambiguous Words and falſe Principles to repreſent the ſtate of this Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſuch as the King affected to have it. By this means was King <hi>James</hi> himſelf in part impoſed upon, (for <hi>Quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid volumus facile credimus</hi>) but his poſterity more, and a great part of the Clergy, and others who adherd to them, in ſo much that they could never ſince tell how to extri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate themſelves out of thoſe falſe Notions, into which the craft and knavery of theſe Flatters had miſlead them, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially under the Byaſs and Prejudice of a ſuppoſed Intereſt. This tempted and encouraged the King many times upon occaſion to exerciſe his ſuppoſed Prerogative: But the people of <hi>England</hi> being an underſtanding people, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:109453:14"/>well knowing their own Rights, could not ſo eaſily be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed upon by Fallacies contrary to their Intereſt. And hence aroſe the fatal difference between King and People, and between the People themſelves, while part to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their illegal Aſſertions, to get Preferments, or being miſled, ſided with the King; and part, and that the greateſt and moſt conſiderable part, ſtood firm to the Laws, and for maintenance of their Rights. And certain it is that thoſe very matters, wherein King <hi>James</hi> and his Succeſſors thus unhappily tranſgreſſed the Laws, were not at all for their benefit, but did meerly gratify inſinuateing Courti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and pernitious Flatterers, to the alienation of the minds of the greateſt and beſt part of the people: So that their cauſe in theſe Differences, was both unjuſt, unprofitable, and pernitious to themſelves. And this was their Caſe in King <hi>Charles</hi> I. and ever ſince.</p>
            <p>But of all the matters wherein they tranſgreſſed the Laws, none was more pernitious, even to themſelves, than <hi>Intermiſſions and unſeaſonable Prorogations and Diſſolutions of Parliaments</hi> contrary to the Laws. For certain it is, and very apparent in the very Conſtitution of our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and conſtant Practice, that <hi>the People of</hi> England <hi>have as much Right to inſpect the Adminiſtration, as the King to exerciſe it.</hi> And had theſe Kings exerciſed this part in ſummoning Parliaments and permiting them to ſit and act according to the Laws, which they are ſworn to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, this would certainly have prevented the miſchiefs which have befaln not only the Nation, but themſelves more eſpecially. For the Majeſty, Honour, and Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the King is for the benefit of the Nation, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſireable, and actually deſired by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> as much as any people in the World. But theſe Intermiſſions and Interruptions of Parliaments, as they ſerved only for the ſecurity of Malefactors and evil Councellors from con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dign Puniſhment, and were for that end procured by them, ſo did they expoſe thoſe Kings to their Knavery, and to be miſled by them to their own ruin.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:109453:15"/>
            <p>The Conſideration of the Cauſes of the Unhappineſs of the laſt race of Kings gives us a clear Proſpect into the <hi>neceſſary Means to make</hi> the next, and the Nation under them, more <hi>happy.</hi> Of which the firſt and principal is a conſtant care and endeavour by all proper means to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the Honour and Eſteem, and the ſincere and cordial profeſſion and practice of TRUE RELIGION AND VER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TUE: and a reſolved ſuppreſſion with a generous indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, of all <hi>Vice and Debauchery,</hi> even thoſe in maska<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rade, ſordid Covetouſnes, and empty Ambition. This is the moſt direct and powerful Means both for the common good of all, and for the private good of each particular, as its <hi>natural effect:</hi> and for obtaining the Divine Favour and Bleſſing which alone gives life to all, as is plain from what I have ſaid before.</p>
            <p>And the <hi>proper meanes</hi> to do this, are good Example; Acts of Grace and Favour, or of Diſpleaſure and Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as occaſion requires; Provident choice of Miniſters, Officers, and Servants; and ſtrict execution of good and effectual Laws.</p>
            <p>Of the great power of <hi>Examples,</hi> when ſet upon the Beacons of high Places in a State (which makes them, if good, as real Lights, and favourable Stars, to ſtear by, if bad, as an <hi>Ignis fatuns</hi> to miſlead poor blinded wandring Souls,) we of this Nation cannot be inſenſible, who have ſeen and felt ſo great unhappy effects of ill ones.</p>
            <p>But it is not ſufficient for a Prince to give good Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in his own perſon and actions, unleſs he take great care alſo that the force of his own be not enervated, baffled and affronted; through his connivance or remiſneſs, by the ill examples of thoſe about him; but eſpecially of his Miniſters, Officers and Servants; that there be not an <hi>Ignis fatuus</hi> among them, but that the whole ſtate may be like a clear Heaven, free from clouds and adorned with illuſtrious radiant Stars; that by a favourable aſpect and benign Influence he encourage ſuch, but with the Storms of Indignation diſperſe all noxious Meteors.</p>
            <pb n="29" facs="tcp:109453:15"/>
            <p>And to this not only the great Importance, but even <hi>Eaſineſs</hi> of the work is no mean <hi>Obligation.</hi> For DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BAUCHERY is a baſe, unmanly, degenerate thing; a compoſition of Folly, Inconſiderateneſs, Impotence, Raſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Madneſs; a mere Impoſture, nothing leſs than what it moſt affects to be thought; nothing but frothy Wit or kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſh Craft, inſtead of true Wiſdom and ſolid Judgment; Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudence and Raſhneſs, inſtead of true generous Courage; nay, many times mere Peuſillanimity and Baſeneſs; or fooliſh fear of the Imputation of Cowardize and Cenſure of vain men, under the greateſt appearance of Courage and Magnanimity; in ſome a greater Monſter among Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional creatures than ever Nature produced among Animals.</p>
            <p>Nor is it leſs baſe, degenerate, and unmanly, in perſons of a higher rank in State, Office, or Employment, than in the meaneſt, but on the contrary a Degeneracy ſo much the greater, and more monſtrous. A debauched Lord a Scan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous Judge, a Covetous, Proud, and Haughty Clergy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, immerſed in ſecular buſineſs, are all groſs Abſurdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. It makes a Title of Honour to become a Lye, and the perſon who bears it, an Impoſtor; ſuch a perſon effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ually abdicates the Nobility of his Anceſſors, is no longer a real object of Honour or Reſpect, but of Indignation and Contempt; and deſerves to be treated as ſuch by all men. Such a <hi>Judge</hi> is worſe: But ſuch a Clergyman worſt of all.</p>
            <p>And therefore as it renders them unfit to be truſted or imployed in great and weighty buſineſs, ſo doth it expoſe them to the contempt of all, but more eſpecially to the juſt Indignation of a Virtuous Prince. Beſides though De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery and Lycentiouſneſs hath long raigned under Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>punity, and be grown to a great height of Impudence, yet hath it not yet ſo far ſpread and prevailed, but that a generous correction and ſuppreſſion of a thing ſo odious in its own nature, would be very gratefull to the beſt and greateſt part of the Nation.</p>
            <p>And thus much upon a civil Conſideration: but we ought
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:109453:16"/>not to reſt here: it is a matter of greater importance than ſo. We ought to conſider the greatneſs of that <hi>Majeſty,</hi> which is concerned in it; in compariſon of whom the whole Earth is but a Mole-hill, but as the duſt of the Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lance, and all mankind are nothing. We ought to conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the <hi>State of the Nation</hi> polluted and defiled with Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptious and Impudent ſin, with open contempt of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and of the precepts of the Goſpel. We ought to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the <hi>Extraordinary Judgments</hi> of God upon ſome of the chief Authors and Promoters, at leaſt by Example and Connivance, of all this Wickedneſs; how they have been blown away with a puff, like chaff before the Wind. We ought to conſider the admirable Mercy, Patience, Long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering, and Clemency of God in granting us ſo <hi>extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary</hi> a <hi>Deliverance,</hi> when in humane probability and conſideration of our own demerit and monſtrous ſins of the Nation, we had more reaſon to have expected nothing but Confuſion and ſome ſevere Judgments upon us. We ought alſo to conſider the <hi>Manner and Circumſtances</hi> of all this, how God hath therein <hi>made bare his Arm,</hi> made his effectual Interpoſition ſo manifeſt and apparent, as is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for the conviction of all, who are not hardned and blinded. And when we have done all this, we ought far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to conſider <hi>what all this calls to us for,</hi> what <hi>Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> it lays upon us, what God expects from us, and what we have further to expect from him according as we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>have our ſelves.</p>
            <p>The abominable abuſes of Popery have run the Reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Churches into ſome contrary Errors and Miſtakes in ſeveral particulars, and among the reſt, concerning exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Acts of Repentance, if I miſtake not. For publick ſins by which the Holy Majeſty of God is publickly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured, a <hi>publick Satisfaction</hi> (in the ſenſe of the Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Chriſtians) is to be made, both by particular perſons, and by whole Nations, when the ſins are National, as they may be by publick Connivance, and other ways. When
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:109453:16"/>a Land is ſo polluted and defiled, it muſt be purged by putting away the evil, by Severity upon the criminals, and by ſome publick Act of Repentance giving Glory to God; and if it do not thus judg it ſelf, it may expect to be judged of the Lord, and the more ſeverely, by how much the longer it is deferred. This is notoriouſly the caſe of this Nation at this time, but what in particular is to be done in it, belongs to others to conſider; I mean as to ſuch publick Satisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, putting away the Evil, and giving Glory to God.</p>
            <p>But certainly whatever elſe be done, it will be to no good purpoſe, but rather a greater Provocation to turn all our ſo favourable a Deliverance into a ſeverer Judgment, if there be not a ſpeedy check and effectual ſtop put to theſe Abominations, which hath been too long neglected and over-looked already. Let any man conſider, eſpecially a Prince, or man in great Authority, how he would reſent it to be publickly affronted and have his Laws or Orders openly contemned. And though the tranſcendent Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of God, be far above the reach of hurt or benefit by any actions of ſo deſpicable beings as mortal men, yet ſuch is his Goodneſs and Benignity to his poor Creatures, that what ever is done, which tends to the real good or hurt of them, he reputes as Service or Diſſervice to himſelf, and what is ill and preſumptuouſly ſo done, as an affront to himſelf. And therefore he is no good Chriſtian, who is not far more moved and concerned for the Honour of God and of his Laws, that they be not publickly affronted and contemned by wicked men, than for any thing which may touch his own Perſon or Dignity. That excellent Being doth not frequently and openly in an extraordinary way inflict his Divine Judgments upon notorious Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, becauſe by his Providence he ſets up Majeſtrates to do it in ordinary way, as his Deputies, and he expects it from them. But he hath in part lately done it in this Nation, in very extraordinary manner: he hath ſent his Fear and Dread upon our Adverſaries, driven out the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:109453:17"/>Heathen, the Cananites, the Authors and Promotors of theſe abominations before us, and brought us into their places of Authority and Power, and expects that we now apply our ſelves to carry on this great Work, and utterly exterminate theſe relicts and old companions of Idolatry and falſe Worſhip. And ſhall we notwithſtanding ſit down to eat and to drink, and riſe up to play? Set to build Houſes for our ſelves, to get Offices and Preferments, or at beſt to provide for our common Rights and Proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; and let the Houſe of God, his Temples in a Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al ſenſe, be defiled and run to ruin in our Land? He hath ſo turned the Hearts of a formidable Army, that they all have either come in and joined with us, ſubmitted to us, or fled from us. And ſhall we now after this make ſuch doubt of his further Divine Aſſiſtance and Bleſſing, as not dare to attempt the Conquering of a few bluſtering De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauches, when God and the beſt part of the Nation ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect it from us, and are ready to approve and concur with us in it; Shall we fool our ſelves in ſuch a caſe as this with that baſe and narrow-ſould Worldly Wiſdom? Let them ſtill out face us, and, if not baſely comply, yet, which is next to it, connive at, and diſſemble, what we cannot be ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of? Nay, by partial and unworthy recommenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſet up in great place in a Chriſtian State, ſuch ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous perſons and evil Examples, as true Chriſtian Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline would humble and caſt out of the Church? and ſo croſs the Providence of God by ſetting up ſuch as he is pulling down? Such Politicoes, who have no more ſenſe of the Honour of God, may poſſibly meet with their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved correction in an Eclipſe of their own. But it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns all, that we do not by neglect or further delay of ſo great a Duty, to which we are lead in ſo ſpecial a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, provoake a change of the courſe of this propitious Providence, ſo as to bring in the Philiſtines again upon us; or correct our lazineſs with ſome new difficulties, or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expected impediments. But ſo much for this.</p>
            <pb n="33" facs="tcp:109453:17"/>
            <p>There is <hi>one thing more in relation to Religion</hi> of great in portance, wherein have been no ſmall miſtakes heretofore committed, and that is <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimity</hi> in Religion. This hath been greatly diſturbed and interrupted by inconſiderate af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectation of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity,</hi> and improper and prepoſterous means for that purpoſe. The moſt natural and proper means to promote both, are 1. To remove all Force (which is contrary to the nature of Religion, as the Ancient Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians generally agree) and Secular Puniſhments upon Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures, 2. To remove all needleſs occaſions of Difference, and unneceſſary Terms of Conformity, eſpecially under Oaths and Subſcriptions, 3. To re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Liturgy, ſo as might moſt conduce to Edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and to gratifie and ſatisfie the Devotion of the moſt Sober and Religious Chriſtians. Againſt this laſt I have not known any thing Objected, but what are the plain Principles and uſual Arguments of the Papiſts againſt the Reformation of their Religion and their Miſſal. This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the Clergy to do, but they muſt be ordered and commiſſionated to do it; the other two may be done by a ſhort Act of Parliament to repeal the Penal Statutes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Proteſtant Diſſenters, the Act of Uniformity, 14. <hi>C.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and with them ſome others inconſiſtent with the true Conſtitution of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Government, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted by Popiſh Counſels to alter the ſame for their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage.</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Civil Matters,</hi> the <hi>Fundamental Error of King</hi> James and his Succeſſors hitherto, (which it is very pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable was promoted by the craft of the Romiſh Emiſſaries, that they might ſtrike in with one party) was that by ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up for Prerogative againſt the Law, <hi>he divided the common Intreſt;</hi> for the King and the People have a <hi>mutual Intreſt</hi> in each other, ſo that what is for the real good of either, is for the common good of both; as in a natural body, what is pernitious to any Member, damnifies the whole. The true <hi>Conſtitution of the</hi> Engliſh <hi>Government</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:109453:18"/>was built upon ſolid Principles of Wiſdom, to give to each all that could be, without prejudice to the other: to the King all the Honour and Majeſty that might be, which was the Honour and Majeſty of the whole; the actual Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, but by Officers authoriſed by Law, and ſworn faithfully to perform their Duty; large Revenues, but to uſe for the publick good, not to alienate at his Pleaſure; and all things to be done in his Name, as the head of the Society, but ſo as he cannot ſtay the ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry courſe of Juſtice at his pleaſure, without violation of the Law: And to the people an Inſpection into the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, and Power to Enquire and Determine con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Miſcariages of it. All which being apparent and undeniable in practice, is a certain argument that the Regal Adminiſtration was deſigned for the Common Good of the whole, of King and People both, as one Body. The <hi>Preſervation</hi> therefore of this Conſtitution doth neceſſarily tend to the ſecurity of the King, as well as of the People; and there can be no better means for this Preſervation, than frequent Seſſions of Parliament according to the Laws, that is, Annual; though to prevent the ſo frequent trouble of Elections, it might be enacted that they ſhould be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen but once in three Years, and ſit at certain times, and when the buſineſs is done, be adjourned or prorogued, but not diſſolved till the laſt Year of the three. A good Act to ſettle ſome ſuch Courſe and regulate Elections, would for the future prevent all ſuch Miſchiefs as have befallen our late Kings, be the moſt effectual means to ſecure the Succeſſion to their poſterity, and preſerve them from all Temptations, and danger of being ſeduced by evil Men. And by this means would Religion and Juſtice make the Nation Flowriſh, and King and People mutually Happy: which every good Man will heartily wiſh and endeavour in his place.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="review">
            <pb n="35" facs="tcp:109453:18"/>
            <head>The REVIEW.</head>
            <p>THus have I followed the train of my thoughts, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what I firſt intended, but not at all beyond, or beſides my Deſign; which was only the Service of God, and the Good of this little part of Mankind, my Country. And I have done it with all Simplicity, Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Plainneſs, without any regard to exactneſs of Method, or any thing elſe but Truth and Uſefulneſs; as I uſe to do with my Friends, and thoſe I moſt wiſh well to. It is true my good Will and Affection, both to Church and State, hath ſome times broaken out into warn expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions, which ingenuous Spirits and well diſpoſed minds can never take amiſs under our Circumſtances: For it is plainly no more than neceſſary. <hi>The times of this</hi> (late) <hi>Ignorance,</hi> (tho many being <hi>willingly ignorant</hi>) <hi>God</hi> in great Mercy <hi>winked at</hi> in our late Deliverance: <hi>But now he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commandeth every one every where to repent.</hi> I am, at leaſt morally, certain, That this Church and State are in a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial manner at this time upon their good behaviour; That if they acquit themſelves well, they may be exceeding pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperous and happy; If they rely too much upon vulgar Politicks, and that Baſtard Wiſdom of the World, they will be intangled, and meet with many and great Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diments and Difficulties; But if they wholly neglect to correſpond and cooperate with the Deſigns of Gods Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence in theſe extraordinary Revolutions, conſider not how great things the Lord hath done for us, but ſtill do wickedly, they ſhall be conſumed, both they and their King; and will ſoon fill up the meaſure of the former Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Preventing</hi> of this, and <hi>Securing</hi> the Proſperity and Happineſs before mentioned, the moſt effectual <hi>Meanes and Method</hi> ſeems to be:</p>
            <pb n="36" facs="tcp:109453:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p n="1">1. That a Day be appointed for <hi>a Solemn Humiliation,</hi> to repreſent truly and plainly the Folly and Madneſs of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable Sins, which have over ſpread the Nation; to unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive and drive us from our Security, and convince us that the late Revolutions were an <hi>Actual Judgment</hi> upon thoſe caſt out, but to us only <hi>an offer of Mercy,</hi> with Judgments ſtill hanging over our heads, ready to fall upon us, if we take not good heed in time; and therefore to excite us to <hi>give Glory to God,</hi> by true <hi>Humiliation,</hi> and a ſpeedy and ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectual <hi>Reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That for this purpoſe ſuch <hi>Laws</hi> as we have already <hi>againſt</hi> any kind of <hi>Debauchery or Profaneneſs,</hi> be ſpedily put in ſtrict execution for the preſent; and, to ſupply the the Defects in them, a more effectual Act be ſpeedily pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, with the moſt proper and natural <hi>Penalties:</hi> as, for the Nobility and Gentry <hi>Degradation</hi> and <hi>Diſability</hi> to hold any Place of Publick Employment, or ſit in Parliament; for others <hi>Whiping, Pillory</hi> and <hi>Infamy;</hi> and further for all, Diſability to give Evidence upon Oath.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That the way may be cleared and inlarged for more <hi>Charity and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nanimity</hi> among Proteſtants, by a <hi>Repeal</hi> of all <hi>Acts againſt Proteſtant Diſſenters,</hi> (which are both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Nature of Chriſtianity, and to the genuine Methods of the Propagation and Preſervation of it, and have proved very Unſucceſsful and Miſchievous) and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the <hi>Act of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niformity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. That ſome effectual Proviſion be made for the more eaſie removing of <hi>Scandalous and unfit Miniſters</hi> out of the Church, and that <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Livings and Preferments</hi> may be committed only to fit and proper Perſons for that Sacred Employment; eſpecially that the Biſhopricks be committed to the moſt pious prudent and induſtrious men. Theſe and ſome other ſuch may make us happs.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
